Guide to the National Smokejumper Association Collection 1919-2023
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
- Smokejumpers: Firefighters from the Sky, 1983-2003 and undated; Series V; 10.5 linear feet.
  - Other Source Video, DVD, Mini-DV, Betacam SP S, Betacam SP L, and VHS, 1988-2003 and undated; Subseries 3; 3.3 linear feet
    - HIPKE Footage, tape 1 of 2 (no 2nd tape), Mini-DV, 2000-2002 (Box 17)
    - HIPKE Summer, Tapes 1,2, and 3, Mini-DVs, 1998 (Box 17)
    - Fire, Mini-DV, undated (Box 17)
    - Smokejumping, Mini-DV, undated (Box 17)
    - Pin Fire, 3 man, Mini-DV, undated (Box 17)
    - Smokejumper-MSO, Mini-DV, undated (Box 17)
    - BLM - Exits, Mini-DV, undated (Box 17)
    - Mann Gulch 50th, Mini-DV, undated (Box 17)
    - 13 Betacam compilation copy reels of Mini-DVs, Betacam SP S and L, undated (Box 17)
    - 3 Betacam reels "Smokejumper Pilot" shot by Missoula Technology Development Center, USDA Forest Service, Betacam SP S, undated (Box 18)
    - 4 Betacam reels "Smokejumper Spotter" shot by Missoula Technology Development Center, USDA Forest Service, Betacam SP S, undated (Box 18)
    - 1939 Experimental Jumps, 3/4" cassette, undated (Box 18)
    - Bobby Montoya - Idaho City and Gila, Les Peppard, Betacam SP L, undated (Box 18)
    - Bill Poppy's, Betacam SP L, undated (Box 18)
    - Eric Hipke - South Canyon, Betacam SP L, undated (Box 18)
    - Jack the Ripper Fire, Tony Petrelli jump footage, Betacam SP L, undated (Box 18)
    - Sawmill Saddle Fire, Betacam SP L, undated (Box 18)
    - Mann Gulch 50th, Betacam SP L, undated (Box 18)
    - Allen Bell Footage, Part 1, Betacam SP L, undated (Box 18)
    - Allen Bell Footage, Part 2, Betacam SP S, undated (Box 18)
    - Hipke 99, Betacam SP S, undated (Box 18)
    - Interview with Secretary of Interior, Bruce Babbit, Betacam SP S, undated (Box 18)
    - NCSB Memorial, Betacam SP S, 2003 (Box 18)
    - SJ 8 Mile Ridge Crash, Betacam SP S, 2003 (Box 18)
    - Ghalor - Early Smokejumpers, Betacam SP S, undated (Box 18)
    - Storm Warning, Sonny Archuleta Concludes, Tony Petrilli, Betacam SP S, undated (Box 18)
    - A, Pick-up Shots, Betacam SP S, undated (Box 18)
    - B, MSO Water Bomb Stills, Betacam SP S, undated (Box 18)
    - C, Son of Pickups, Betacam SP S, undated (Box 18)
    - D, Daughter of Pickups, Betacam SP S, undated (Box 18)
    - U.S. Invasions- Japanese Incendiary Balloons, VHS, undated (Box 19)
    - Allen Bell, BLM-Hollywood, VHS, undated (Box 19)
    - Smokejumper training, Missoula, transfer from 8mm, VHS, 1952 (Box 19)
    - Smokejumpers, VHS, undated (Box 19)
    - Caribou, VHS, undated (Box 19)
    - Early Jumps with Eagle Parachute - rip cord, VHS, undated (Box 19)
    - Boise Jump Season Highlights, VHS, 1999 (Box 19)
    - Hipke Fire Video, VHS, 1998 (Box 19)
    - International Crown Fire Modeling Experiments, Northwest Territories, VHS, 1997 (Box 19)
    - World Fires Victoria, Where the Fire Meets the People, VHS, undated (Box 19)
    - 3 tapes of conscientious objectors discussing their time as smokejumpers during WWII, labeled MCAT 122380, 122411, and 122412, SVHS, undated (Box 19)
    - Telephone Creek: 1950 Smokejumper Documentary, VHS, undated (Box 19)
    - Storm King Mountain Technologies: Developments in Fire Shelters, VHS, undated (Box 19)
    - Season of Fire, Idaho Public Television, VHS, undated (Box 19)
    - Fire Line, Idaho Public Television, VHS, undated (Box 19)
    - Fire Wars, Nova, PBS, VHS, undated (Box 19)
    - 1988 Yellowstone Fires, VHS (Box 19)
    - DVD #1 - Interviews with Marge Kuehn-Tabor, Chuck Flack, and Jim Veitch, undated (Box 22)
    - DVD #2 - Interviews with Mike McMillan, Rod Dow, and Burt Mitman, undated (Box 22)
    - DVD #3 - Interviews with Murry Taylor, Dewey Warner, and Mark Corbet, undated (Box 22)
    - DVD #4 - Interviews with David "Skinny" Beals and Dave Nani, undated (Box 22)
    - DVD #5 - Interviews with Richard Tracy, Lynn Sprague, Robert Kersh, and Cathleen Lowe, undated (Box 22)
    - DVD #6 - Interview with Elmer Neufeld, undated (Box 22)
    - DVD #7 - Interview with Eric Hipke, undated (Box 22)
    - DVD #8 - Interviews with Steve Nemore and Phil and Jake Brollier, undated (Box 22)
    - DVD #9 - Interviews with Neal Hitchcock, Roy Johnson, Rusty Warbiss, Roy Wenger, and Bruce Babbitt, undated (Box 22)
    - DVD #10 - Interviews with Gary "Gramps" Johnson, Jerry Zumwalt, and Gene Hobbs, undated (Box 22)
    - DVD #11 - Interviews with George Cross, Bob Nicol, and Stewart "Lloyd" Johnson, undated (Box 22)
    - DVD #12 - Interviews with Rob and Karen Morrow, Gregg Anderson, and Tony Petrilli, undated (Box 22)
    - DVD #13 - Interview with Wayne Webb, undated (Box 22)
    - DVD #14 - Interview with "Wild" Bill Yensen, undated (Box 22)
  - Video Not Used, 2000; Subseries 4; 4 items
    This subseries contains film collected but not used in the making of Smokejumpers: Firefighters from the Sky.
    - Up in Flames, Forest History Society documentary, Betacam SP S and VHS dub, undated (Box 19)
    - Escape: Fire in Mann Gulch, VHS, 2000 (Box 19)
    - The Rockies, VHS, 2000 (Box 19)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1983-2003 and undated; Subseries 5; 0.2 linear feet
    This subseries contains research and contracts related to the making of Smokejumpers: Firefighters from the Sky.
    - Contracts and correspondence, 1999-2003 (Box-folder 21/1)
    - Research, undated (Box-folder 21/2)
    - A Pictorial History of Smokejumping by Stan Cohen, 1983 (Box-folder 21/3)
    - Newsclippings, 2001 and undated (Box-folder 21/4)
    - Videocassette Case Artwork, undated (Box-folder 21/5)
- There I Was! the Smokejumper Storyteller Project Interviews, 2014; Series VI; 1.0 linear feet
  This series contains interviews of smokejumpers for the There I Was! project conducted by John Driscoll.
  - Smokejumper Oral Histories Collected in 2014, Binder, Includes Interview Summaries and Releases (Box 23)
- Personal Papers of Smokejumpers, 1938-2016; Series VII; 0.3 linear feet
  This series contains personal papers of former smokejumpers.
  - Ball, Herman, 1950s; Subseries 1; 0.1 linear feet
    Herman Ball was a smokejumper who jumped the 1950 and 1951 seasons in Missoula. He was recruited by the Central Intelligence Agency for their operations in Taiwan; he and other smokejumpers trained Chinese nationalist troops in survival tactics and parachuting. This subseries contains photographs of Ball's activities in Taiwan in the 1950s as well as a photograph of Marana Army Air Field in Arizona, a CIA base of operations during the Vietnam War.
    - Photographs, Training Nationalist Troops, Western Enterprises, Inc., Taiwan, Taipei Guest House, Marana Army Air Field, 1950s (Box-folder 24/1)
  - Brennan, Robert (Bob), 1938-1942; Subseries 2; 0.2 linear feet
    Robert J. Brennan was a pioneer smokejumper in the summer of 1941. This collection contains photographs, journals, and a jump log from the Nine Mile camp in western Montana as well as journals from Brennan's previous Forest Service posts.
    - Journals, 1938-1942 (Box-folder 24/2)
    - Jump Log, 1941 (Box-folder 24/3)
    - Photographs, Part 1 of 4, 1941-1942 (Box-folder 24/4)
    - Photographs, Part 2 of 4, 1941-1942 (Box-folder 24/5)
    - Photographs, Part 3 of 4, 1941-1942 (Box-folder 24/6)
    - Photographs, Part 4 of 4, 1941-1942 (Box-folder 24/7)
    - NSA Bumper Sticker and Membership Card, 1941 and undated (Box-folder 24/8)
    - Photographs and Slides, 1940s (Box-folder 24/9)
    - Oral History, undated (Box-folder 24/10)
  - Grenager, Lyle, 1951-1954; Subseries 3; 0.1 linear feet
    Lyle Grenager was a smokejumper out of Missoula, Montana from 1946 to 1951. He was recruited by the Central Intelligence Agency in 1951 to assist with their covert operations in Taiwan to train a resistance force of Nationalist Chinese troops. This subseries includes photos from Grenager's time in Taiwan including playing on the basketball team for the CIA's front company, Western Enterprises, Inc., and meeting the president of the Republic of China, Chiang Kai-shek.
    - Photographs, CIA Activities in Taiwan and China, Western Enterprises, Inc., Lou Rucker, 1951-1952 (Box-folder 24/11)
    - Photographs, Chinese National Basketball Team Versus Western Enterprises, Inc., 1952 (Box-folder 24/12)
    - Photographs, Chiang Kai-shek, Soong Mei-ling, Herman Ball, Lou Rucker, July 11, 1953 (Box-folder 24/13)
    - Portrait of Lou Rucker, 1950s (Box-folder 24/14)
      Lou Rucker was head of the parachute training program in Taiwan. A former colonel in the U.S. Army, he was also Lyle Grenager's roommate at the Taipei Guest House, the first headquarters for CIA operations in Taiwan.
  - Kurowski, Ed J., 2016; Subseries 4; 0.1 linear feet and 16 Megabytes
    Ed J. Kurowski was a smokejumper who jumped his rookie season in Missoula, Montana in the summer of 1961. Kurowski was from Green Bay, Wisconsin and studied forest engineering at the University of Wisconsin. This subseries contains the collective memoir of many smokejumpers who rookied in 1961 in Missoula, Montana; Ed Kurowski compiled, edited, and authored the memoir.
    - The Way We Were: 1961, 2016 (Box-folder 25/1)
    - The Way We Were: 1961, 2016 (Electronic file Electronic File)
      This is an electronic version of Kurowski's memoir, please contact Archives and Special Collections for additional information.
  - Mathews, Jack, 1986-2001; Subseries 5; 0.1 linear feet
    Jack Mathews was a smokejumper in Missoula, Montana in the summer of 1948. He was recruited by the Central Intelligence Agency and spent his entire career with them. This subseries contains correspondence written by Mathews concerning various aspects of his service as a military advisor in Laos in the late 1950s, clippings of an article he wrote, photographs, and various other correspondence and notes. There is also a detailed letter he wrote to John MacLean about his article on the smokejumpers at Mann Gulch.
    - Correspondence and Background Information, 1986-2001 (Box-folder 24/15)
  - Pickard, Lloyd A. "Chuck", 1948-2005; Subseries 6; 0.2 linear feet
    Lloyd A. "Chuck" Pickard was a smokejumper in Missoula, Montana who trained in the summer of 1948. He was a squadleader out of Nine Mile in the summer of 1949 and was supposed to jump on the Mann Gulch fire near Helena, Montana, but traded places with Bill Hellman. This subseries includes photographs, Mann Gulch research materials, materials collected by Jack Mathews, and smokejumper reunion materials.
    - Correspondence, National Smokejumper Association Business, Museum of Mountain Flying, 2003-2005 (Box-folder 24/16)
    - Earl Cooley Letter to Francis Anywaush, May 26, 1987 (Box-folder 24/17)
    - Mann Gulch Articles, 1949-1993 (Box-folder 24/18)
    - Mann Gulch Newspaper Clippings, 1949-2003 (Box-folder 24/19)
    - National Parachute Jumpers-Riggers Card, Region 1 Signals Card, Smoke Jumpers Athletic Fund Dance, 1950 (Box-folder 24/20)
    - Philip McVey Materials Collected by Jack Mathews, 1986-1999 (Box-folder 24/21)
    - Photograph, Chuck Pickard in Police Uniform with Fred Barnowsky, Fort Lauderdale, Florida, circa 1952 (Box-folder 24/22)
    - Photographs, Mann Gulch, 2003-2005 (Box-folder 24/23)
    - Photographs, Mann Gulch Memorial, National Wildland Firefighter Memorial, From Jerry Linton, May 8, 1991 (Box-folder 24/24)
    - Photographs, Missoula, Skydiving, 1949-1950 (Box-folder 24/25)
    - Photographs, Smokejumpers, Montana, Idaho, 1948-1953 (Box-folder 24/26)
    - Photographs and Articles, Priest River, Coolin Ranger Station, Idaho, 1946-1947 (Box-folder 24/27)
    - Photographs and Letter, Smokejumper Reunions, 1984-2004 (Box-folder 24/28)
    - Photographs and Reproductions, Nine Mile, Training, 1948-1950 (Box-folder 24/29)
    - Reminiscence of Mann Gulch Events, 1999 (Box-folder 24/30)
    - Smokejumping and Smokejumper Reunion Ephemera, 1999-2004 and undated (Box-folder 24/31)
- Accession 2018-066, 1947-2017; Series VIII; 0.4 linear feet
  This series contains folders of material by or about fifteen smokejumpers. All folders include a 'submittal form' documenting contents and providing context. The materials were compiled and donated for inclusion in the NSA collection by John Driscoll. Driscoll has indicated jump years and base on each folder.
  - Ray G. Beasley, 2014; reproduction of photo of Beasley and his wife, Jane, at CIA Headquarters. Invitation to CIA Museum ceremony, 2014. (File 26/1)
  - Bob Benzie, undated; Map indicating single fire jump of Benzie in 1956. Database printout documenting his activity. (File 26/2)
  - Walt E. Currie, 1978; Three photographs by Driscoll of MSO Alaska Booster Crew, including Currie, 1978 (File 26/3)
  - John Brian Driscoll, 1968-2017; Smokejumper patch from 1968 fire season. Signed copy of book: Smokejumpers of the CIA. Color slides dated 1977, identified as "fire season out of Missoula Fire Depot." Photographs identified as "unknown jumpers exiting DC-3, probably NW of Missoula in 1968." (File 26/4)
  - Lester E. Gahler, undated; DVD: Leap of Faith: CO Smokejumping During World War II. DVD description states: Includes video footage by former CO Smokejumper Lester Gahler. (File 26/5)
  - Clarence Douglas Getz, undated; Reproductions of photographs. One identified as Silver City Fire Crew either 1959 or 1960. Others identified as "we think this is the Grangeville Fire Crew." (File 26/6)
  - Gary W. Grandquist, 1978; photograph: "10 man Volpar load out of McGrath headed for Canadian boarder." Photo by John Driscoll. (File 26/7)
  - Lyle D. Grenager, 2015; Typewritten notes by Driscoll of interview with Grenager. Typescript of article printed in June 25, 2004 "Clark Fork Chronicle." (File 26/8)
  - George King, 1948 and undated; undated photographs: Old Hale Field, first civilian helicopters, ford tri-motor dropping cargo, smokejumper training at Nine Mile. Castle Creek crew (1948). (File 26/9)
  - Fred Koons, 1948; photos of Fred Koons and George King, and possibly Jerry Linton. (File 26/10)
  - Gerald J. Linton, 1948; photocopies of photographs in other folders in this series. (File 26/11)
  - Philip R. McVey, 1948; original and copy photographs - McVey at Castle Creek on Middle Fork of Clearwater. (File 26/11)
  - Avery J. "Jack" Nott, 1950 and undated; original photographs - Pattee Canyon Jump for 20th Century Fox, 1950; Marble Canyon, Arizona jump; Nott and Johnson pilot Larry Florek; unidentified jumpers, planes, and equipment. (File 26/12)
  - Richard A. Peterson, 2013; Privately published book: Richard Arnold Peterson and Eve Ridgely Chapline Peterson. (File 26/13)
  - Glenn Smith, 1949 and undated; photograph of Skeezeck and Smitty, 1949. Smith in truck, undated. (File 26/14)
  - Robert H. Sprute, 1949 and undated; Bound memoir: Smokejumpers, Aerial Firefighters of the West. The Way We Were, 1961. A collection memoir [by] Ed. J. Kurowski. Clipping. Database printout of jumps. (File 26/15)